Department of History Records, ca. 1900-[ongoing]
Smith College Archives
Department of History Records
ca. 1900-[ongoing]
Smith College. Dept. of History.
RG 52 UUID:d6d2337d-cba3-4b7c-b168-f6255e77fe0c
8 boxes (3.3 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
The records contain some historical documents on the teaching of history at Smith College, general records of the History Department and reading lists and course lists for the department. There are documents related to the Mendenhall Prize in History and on the symposium "Faces of Tradition" in honor of Klemens von Klemperer held April 2-4, 1987. Access to Box 2 is restricted.
Various lecturers taught history courses from the beginning of Smith College in 1875 until 1894 when a Department of History was more formally established with Prof. Charles Downer Hazen as the resident head. Prof. Hazen remained in this position until 1914 when Prof. John Spencer Bassett became head of the department; Prof. Bassett was responsible for the establishment of the department's publication Smith College Studies in History, 1915-2003. By 1919-1920 the teaching staff included five full professors, two associate professors, two assistant professors and three instructors plus two readers.
The Department of History files contain correspondence, reading lists, lecture and student notes from classes, publications and other material documenting the history of the department.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The minutes of the History Department are restricted for 75 years.
History of the Collection
The records were created by Department of History of Smith College and donated to the College Archives.
Additional Information
Related Material
Researchers should also view:
RG 42. Faculty biographical files on the Department of History faculty
RG 32. Office of the President for records on the Department of History
Reports of the President
Annual Circulars/Bulletins
Fuller, Mary Breese, "Development of History and Government in Smith College, 1875-1920, with a List of Publications of the Faculty and Alumnae," Smith College Studies in History v.5, no. 3 (April 1920).
- Historical information (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Introductory Course in History: Digest of Material Obtained by Questionnaire from Sixty American Colleges and Universities, by Sidney R. Packard 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- History Club 1896-1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Departmental rosters and committee lists 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Memorandum and announcements 19 -19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Honors requirements and documents (Box 1, Folder 6)
- NEA Summer Institutes 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- Departmental minutes 1914-1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Departmental minutes--RESTRICTED 1922-1932 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Departmental minutes--RESTRICTED 1932-1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Departmental minutes--RESTRICTED 1938-1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Reading lists for History 11 1919-1966 (Box 3)
- Course lists - General (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Course lists - History 12 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Course lists - History 13 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Course lists - History 22-29 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Course lists - History 30-31 1939-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Course lists - History 32-36 1930s-1958 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Course lists - History 37-49 1930s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Course lists - History 100-102 1960s-1970s (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Course lists - History 103 1960s (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Course lists - History 114-425 1924-1958 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Course lists - History 294-295 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Course lists - History 383 2000 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Courses History 100-273 - Mid-term and final examination questions 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Lecture notes for English history Early 1900s (Box 5)
- Student notes for History 4a - unidentified student 1909-1910 (Box 6)
- Mendenhall Prize in History 1974-1991 (Box 7)
- Records re Symposium "Faces of Tradition" in honor of Klemens von Klemperer, held April 2-4, 1987 1986-1987 (Box 8)
- Smith College studies in history 1915-2003 (Box 8)